A Guide to the Papers of Paul Bowles, 1985-1989
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Paul Bowles 1985-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10501-j
This collection contains 46 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Jeffrey Miller on April 25, 1990.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains electrostatic copies of the original manuscript of the full score of his Concerto for Two Pianos, Winds & Percussion, and letters to Peter Garland chiefly concerning the publication of the Concerto but also discussing the sale of his manuscripts to the University of Virginia, music for Bernardo Bertolucci's The Sheltering Sky, censorship by Moroccan customs, a suggested publication of his selected instrumental works, and his health.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - Concerto For Two Pianos, Winds & Percussion, composed by Paul Bowles ca. 1985-1989, Musical Scores (EC). Electrostatic copy in its original condition, 171 p.
  - Concerto For Two Pianos, Winds & Percussion, composed by Paul Bowles ca. 1985-1989, Musical Scores (EC). Electrostatic copy with instrumental markings written in by Paul Bowles, 171 p.
  - Concerto For Two Pianos, Winds & Percussion, composed by Paul Bowles ca. 1985-1989, Musical Scores (EC). Electrostatic copy in its final condition, 174 p.
  - Concerto For Two Pianos, Winds & Percussion, composed by Paul Bowles ca. 1985-1989, Musical Scores (CRC). Oversize camera-ready copy and other related material, 184 p.
  - Miscellaneous Musical Scores by Paul Bowles n.d., Musical Scores (EC)
    Obtained from microfilm belonging to the Humanities Research Center [The University of Texas at Austin]
- Letters Concerning the Copyright for Concerto for Two Pianos, Winds and Percussion
  - Theodore Presser Co. to Peter Garland 1987-1988, 4 TLS
    Grants permission for Garland to publish Concerto for Two Pianos, Winds and Percussion
- Letters from Paul Bowles to Peter Garland
  - Mentions attempts of Jeffrey Miller to dispose of material sent to him by Garland, his meeting Harry Partch in 1968, and Conquest of Mexico music December 12, 1985, TLS, 1 p.
  - Writes of Jeffrey Miller's arrangement to sell Bowles material to the University of Virginia, offers to send other copies of his musical works not heard by Garland, and asks for a copy of his Night WaltzJanuary 4, 1986, ALS, 1 p.
  - Discusses further the proposal to sell some of his material to the University of Virginia and agrees to send a copy of A Picnic CantataMarch 20, 1986, ANS, 1 p.
  - Writes of the increase in censorship since the United States raid on Tripoli, customs refusal to allow him a transcript sent by a New York publisher, the sale of his material to the University of Virginia, and a renewed request for The Conquest of MexicoMay 13, 1986, TLS, 1 p.
  - Informs Garland that the censors finally passed a tape of The Conquest of MexicoJune 24, 1986, TLS, 1 p.
  - Thanks Garland for Soundings, Artspace, with Apple Blossoms, note sent on the verso of a color photograph of Paul Bowles standing in front of [Tangiers ?] August 22, 1986, ANS, 1 p.
  - Refers to an operation to save his leg from gangrene and his intentions of sending a tape of the songs included in the Soundings volume October 15, 1986, ALS, 1 p.
  - Responds to Garland's suggestion of assembling a Selected Instrumental Works and discusses publishing a collection of his music, much of which is not included on the Humanities Research Center list of his musical works November 12, 1986, TLS, 1 p.
  - Lists the titles of his music that he would like to see published and refers to a visit by Henrietta Yurchenco in 1955 December 3, 1986, TLS, 1 p.
  - Discusses the problem with copyright over the Concerto For Two Pianos, Winds and Percussion claimed by the Theodore Presser Company December 28, 1986, ALS, 1 p.
  - Bowles further discusses the Concerto, Paul Bowles music at the University of Virginia, and attending the ash-scattering ceremony for Brion Gysin January 20, 1987, TLS, 1 p.
  - Refers to a tape sent to William Burroughs by Garland and his task of translating two of his own books into French February 19, 1987, APCS
  - Suggests three other titles to be included in the book, Sonata for Two Pianos, Night Waltz, and The Flute Sonata, which he sends on a tape May 18, 1987, APCS
  - Is unable to identify some of the pieces listed in Garland's last letter and warns that the tape he wants to send may be held up by the censors June 30, 1987, APCS
  - Has not received either the Harrison book or the cassette mailed by Garland August 17, 1987, APCS
  - Does not understand Theodore Presser Company's claim to own copyright to Concerto for Two PianosAugust 25, 1987, TLS, 1 p.
  - Discusses the list of his musical material already in the possession of Garland and makes definite suggestions of what to include in their publication of his music September 10, 1987, TLS, 1 p.
  - Informs Garland that he has received the Harrison book and that he likes it September 18, 1987, APCS
  - Has finally gotten a good recording machine which facilitates copying so sends the long promised tape recording of several of his pieces to Garland and recommends the book Blood Meridian by Cormac McCarthy November 2, 1987, TLS, 1 p.
  - Lists the music selections from out of the number sent by Garland that he feels worthwhile to include in their book and mentions possible problems in getting permission to reprint some of them February 16, 1988, TLS, 1 p.
  - Comments on the letters of [Silvestre?] Revueltas sent by Garland for him to read and suggests that he eliminate the passages showing Revueltas'"abject, almost masochistic attitude towards his wife." March 9, 1988, TLS, 1 p.
  - Expresses his pleasant surprise that Presser gave permission to publish the Concerto for Two Pianos, hopes that Schirmer will give permission to reprint Music for a Farce, and describes his problems in getting a tape of a Paul Bowles Concert done in Nice from the censor's office May 11, 1988, TLS, 1 p.
  - Mentions his recovery from a hernia operation, his appreciation that Moroccan doctors make house calls, and tries to suggest a way to use the poor quality electostatic copy of the ConcertoJuly 18, 1988, TLS, 1 p.
  - Reports his recent return from a television broadcast in Paris and the beginning of his corrections on the copy of the Concerto, and mentions future journalistic visits he must endure November 21, 1988, TLS, 1 p.
  - Describes the problems he has found in his copy of The Two Piano ConcertoDecember 12, 1988, ALS, 2 p.
  - Apologizes for losing the score of the Concerto and describes his unusual storage problems February 5, 1989, TLS, 1 p.
  - Describes his difficulties in adding more dynamics to the score of the Concerto, and his problems with the Moroccan censors after an acquaintance in New York sent him a copy of Satanic Verses as a joke April 23, 1989, TLS, 1 p.
  - Thanks Garland for his additional instructions for correcting the Concerto and hopes to get a copy of the New World record smuggled in someone's luggage May 19, 1989, APCS
  - Writes a short report on his progress with the ConcertoMay 28, 1989, ALS, 1 p.
  - Asks for better copies of certain pages of the Concerto which are illegible on his copy May 31, 1989, TLS, 1 p.
  - Writes concerning the offer of Phillip Ramey to take the original of the Concerto to New York and make a new copy of it there for Bowles to correct June 15, 1989, TLS, 1 p.
  - Asks when Garland needs to know if Bowles can do a preface for the book July 20, 1989, APCS
  - Reports the arrival of the Concerto, thanks Garland for all his hard work in restoring it, and mentions a letter from the director of Orchestre Cannes Provence-Cote d'Azur suggesting they play the piece in Cannes next year August 3, 1989, TLS, 1 p.
  - Expresses his extreme dislike for the unauthorized biography of himself by Christopher Sawyer-Laucanno (1951- ) which he characterizes as malicious, biased, irresponsible, sloppy, and full of misstatements and inventions, and mentions that the producer [Bernardo] Bertolucci wants him to write a little music for his film The Sheltering SkyAugust 29, 1989, TLS, 1 p.
  - Writes that he is busy with the Bertolucci film in which he has a part, and that the preface to the concerto volume and contracts with Pedro Almodovar for film rights have both been lost in the mail November 4, 1989, TLS, 1 p.
  - Reports the arrival of the Concerto and complains about the inudation of rain during the last two and a half weeks causing severe leakage in his home and delays in Bertolucci's filming schedule December 5, 1989, TLS, 1 p.
- Microfilm
  - Positive microfilm copies of assorted Paul Bowles Musical Scores belonging to the Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin n.d., MSS (Microfilm)